<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Act anent the maintenance of the armie for nine moneths, and for retention of one and a half of the anualrent [sic] of eight of the hundred</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1048B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875501</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152355</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92475)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152355)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2294:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Act anent the maintenance of the armie for nine moneths, and for retention of one and a half of the anualrent [sic] of eight of the hundred</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>At head of title: Edinburgh 20. February 1647.</note>
                  <note>"Act of the Convention of Estates, holden at Edinburgh the fifteeenth of August, 1643. for the loane and taxt [sic]" -- p. 7-20.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152355:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Edinburgh <date>20.February 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>Act anent the Maintenance of the Armie for nine Moneths, and for Retention of one and a half of the Anualrent of eight of the Hundred.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Eſtates of Parliament now conveened, in this ſixth Seſsion of the firſt Triennall Parliament, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to their ſerious Conſideration the long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the preſent rebellion of our unnatural Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, and of the invaſion from the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and the great expences that they muſt ſuſtaine for ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the ſame, and carrying on of the War; and how neceſſary and incumbent it is to them, that ſome ſolid &amp; ſetled way be provided for the conſtant maintenance of the forces, Horſe &amp; Foot; Have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concluded, that ſix thouſand Foot, twelve hundred Horſe, two hundred and ten Dragooners ſhall be intertained and keeped upon pay, towards the proſecution of the War againſt theſe Rebels and Invaders, untill the ſame, by the bleſſing of the God of Hoſtes, he brought to an happy end; Have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought fit to ſtatute and ordain, Like as for that effect they enact and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that ilk Shire and Burgh within this Kingdome, ſhall be lyable and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieged, in payment of the particular ſums of money, and that Monethly, and with the Suſpenſion underwritten, for the intertainment of the Forces, Horſe, Foot, and Dragooners above written, and that for the ſpace of nine Moneths, (whereof the moſt part of the firſt Moneth is already aſſigned by a former Act, towards the payment of the Regiments which ſerved at <hi>Philip-Hauch</hi>) beginning the firſt termes payment from the tenth of January laſt-by-paſt, and ſo forth, after the expiring of that Moneth, to continue for other eight Moneths thereafter, untill the tenth of October next enſuing. But becauſe the moſt part of that Moneths maintenance is either aſſigned or payed, and that the Forces abovementioned is ordained to pay all their intertainment, and take no free Quarters, which the Eſtates have ordained to be refounded unto them at the end of the Moneth, after their ingagement: Therefore it is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and ordained, that for payment of their bygone Moneth, the Shires and Burrows ſhall readily pay, and deliver to Sir <hi>John Weemes</hi> of <hi>Bogie,</hi> Generall Commiſſar, and Collector of this Kingdome, who is heereby appointed to pay the Regiments their ſeverall proportions of Monethly maintenance, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152355:2"/>to the diviſions after following, that portion of the ſaid firſt Moneths maintenance not formerly aſſigned, and alſo to pay and deliver unto him the whole other eight Moneths maintenance, and that Monethly, beginning the payment for the ſecond Moneth upon the firſt day of March, for payment of the preſent Armie, betwixt the tenth day of February, to the tenth day of March, in reſpect the ſaid interveening dayes, are the leaſt which can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for in-gathering of this maintenance, and ſo forth Monethly thereafter from each firſt day of the Moneth to another, during the continuance of this preſent maintenance, except what is ſuſpended in manner after mentioned.</p>
            <p>Followes the ſums payable by the Shires, which is underwritten, and that Monethly, by the ſpace of nine Moneths, from the tenth of January laſt by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt, to the tenth of October next to come, <hi>viz. Orkney</hi> of Monethly pay, 1143. l. <hi>Innernes,</hi> 4176. l..<hi>Caithnes,</hi> 945. l. <hi>Cromartie,</hi> 99. l. <hi>Sutherland,</hi> 423. l. <hi>Nairne,</hi> 315. l. <hi>Elgine,</hi> 1890. l. <hi>Aberdeene,</hi> 6543 l. <hi>Bamfe,</hi> 1431. l. <hi>Kincar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine,</hi> 1566. l. <hi>Forfar,</hi> 5004. l. <hi>Perth,</hi> 8001. l. <hi>Fife,</hi> 6642. l. <hi>Striveling,</hi> 2538. l. <hi>Kinros,</hi> 144. l. <hi>Clakmannan,</hi> 522. l. <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 4167. l. <hi>Linlithgow,</hi> 1746. l. <hi>Hadingtoun,</hi> 3384. l. <hi>Berwick,</hi> 3555. l. <hi>Roxburgh</hi> 5778. l. <hi>Selkirk,</hi> 1278. l. <hi>Pebles,</hi> 1638. l. <hi>Lanerk,</hi> 5382. l. <hi>Air,</hi> 6066. l. <hi>Wigtoun</hi> and Stuartrie of <hi>Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cudbright,</hi> 4374 l. <hi>Drumfreis,</hi> 4446. l. <hi>Renfrew,</hi> 2205. l. <hi>Dumbartan,</hi> 1233. l. <hi>Argyle,</hi> 2907. l. <hi>Bute,</hi> 459. l.</p>
            <p>Follows the ſums payable Monethly by the Burrows, conform to their taxt Roll, <hi>viz. Edinburgh,</hi> 5175. l. <hi>Perth,</hi> 810. l. <hi>Dundie,</hi> 1200. l. <hi>Aberdeene,</hi> 1260. l. <hi>Striveling,</hi> 240 l. <hi>Linlithgow,</hi> 324. l. S. <hi>Andrews 780 l. <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> 1530. l. <hi>Air,</hi> 342. l. <hi>Hadingtoun,</hi> 324 l. <hi>Dyſert,</hi> 270. l. <hi>Kirkcaldie,</hi> 600. l. <hi>Monroſe,</hi> 324. l. <hi>Cowper,</hi> 216. l. <hi>Anſtruther</hi> eaſter, 180. l. <hi>Drumfreis,</hi> 270. l. <hi>Innernes,</hi> 450. l. <hi>Breechen,</hi> 120. l. <hi>Irwing,</hi> 252. l. <hi>Elgine,</hi> 135. l. Jedburgh</hi> 126. l. <hi>Kirkcudbright,</hi> 80. l. Wigtoun, 135. l. <hi>Pettinweyme,</hi> 120. <hi>Dumfermline</hi> 162. l. <hi>Dumbartan,</hi> 162. l. Renfrew, 90. l.. <hi>Lanerk,</hi> 162. l. <hi>Aberbrothok,</hi> 81. l. <hi>Bruntiland,</hi> 216. l. <hi>Pebles,</hi> 108. l. <hi>Carrail,</hi> 216. l. <hi>Kinghorn,</hi> 108. l. <hi>Tayne,</hi> 90. l. <hi>Selkirk,</hi> 126 l. <hi>Anſtruther</hi> weſter, 54. l. <hi>Culros,</hi> 90. l. <hi>Dumbar,</hi> 180. l. <hi>Bamfe,</hi> 72. l. <hi>Whithorn,</hi> 45. l. <hi>Forfar,</hi> 27. l. <hi>Rotheſay,</hi> 60. l. Forres, 54. l. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therglen,</hi> 45. l. <hi>Northberwick,</hi> 36. l. <hi>Culane,</hi> 27. l. <hi>Narne,</hi> 36. l. <hi>Lawder,</hi> 45. l. <hi>Innerkeithing,</hi> 90. l. <hi>Kilrynnie,</hi> 27. l. <hi>Annand,</hi> 30. l. <hi>Lochmaben,</hi> 18. l. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhare,</hi> 27. l. <hi>Galloway,</hi> 9. l. <hi>Dingwal,</hi> 18. l. <hi>Queensferrie,</hi> 108. l. <hi>Dornoch,</hi> 10. l.</p>
            <p>And for the better inbringing and collecting of the foreſaids ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, for payment and intertainment of the forces abovewritten, as well Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers as Souldiers, The Eſtates of Parliament Nominates and Appointes the ſaid Sir <hi>John Weymes</hi> of <hi>Bogie</hi> Generall Commiſſar, Theſaurer, or Collector of this Kingdome for the ſaid Army, with power to him to appoint Deputes one or mo in each Shire: And that other Collectors in ſuch Burghs and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes be appointed by him in ſuchlike manner, as is contained in the Act of Loan and Taxt; which Collector deputes as well of Shires as Pariſhes, and Clerks of Shires for that effect, ſhall have ſuch Fees as is allowed in the Act of Convention, made anent the in-gathering of the Loan and Taxt, and that to be uplifted out of the ſaid Shires and Pariſhes within the ſame, by and attour the Monethly maintenance, and the Burghs to be free, in reſpect they collect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152355:2"/>their proportions upon their own charges; And with power to the ſaid Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Commiſſar and Collector foreſaid, to appoint a Clerk of collection whom he ſhall be pleaſed to nominate, and for whom he ſhall be anſwerable; Which Clerk of collection ſo to be appointed by him, Shall have the ſum of two hundreth Merks Sterling, to be payed out of the ſaid Monethly Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for his paines and charges which he muſt undergoe in collection of the Moneths Maintenance above written: And it is Declared, and Ordained, That the Letters and Charges to follow upon this preſent Act, for imlpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of every Head and Article thereof, ſhall bee raiſed and direct at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Weymes</hi> Generall Commiſſar and Collector foreſaid, againſt the Subcollectors of Shires, Magiſtrates of Burrows, Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of Pariſhes, Heritors, Fewars, Liferenters, and others adebted in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſeverall proportions of the Maintenance now impoſed, with reſervation of the ſuſpenſions underwritten, in the ſame manner, and with the ſame proviſions and certifications as is contained in the Act of convention of Eſtates made for the Loane and Taxt, and that they have Letters of relief as is ordained by the ſaid Act of convention.</p>
            <p>And for the more ſpeedie ingathering of this Maintenance: It is ordained, if any Shire, Burgh, or Perſon therein deſigned, be deficient in paying of their Monethlie proportion, That the ſaid Generall Commiſſar ſhall have Power, Authorite, and Warrand, to raiſe in each Shire eight or ten Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to be intertained at the ordinary rates, and preſent eſtabliſhment to bee payed to them by the deficients, by and attour their proportionable Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; And ordains the Committee of Warre within each Shire <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> to be aiding and aſſiſting to the ſaid Theſaurer, both in furniſhing of Troupers, and inbringing the Maintenance: Or otherwiſe, The Eſtates of Parliament hereby gives him power to require orders from the General Officers, that they would command ſuch a number of their neareſt lying and adjacent Souldiers, Horſe, or Foot, as he ſhall demand, to repaire unto him and bee directed by him, for inbringing and uplifting of that proportion of the ſaid Maintenance which ſhall not be readily payed, and theſe to have free Quarters by directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Generall Commiſſar or his Deputes in the ſeverall Shires, upon the Deficient Shires, Burghs, or Perſons, ay and while they make ready payment of their part of the ſaid Maintenance: And the Eſtates or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines the Generall Officers, To readily anſwer the ſaid Theſaurer his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire foreſaid.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is conceived by the Eſtates of Parliament, That ſundrie Shires or parts thereof, or Burghs, are burnt, waſted, or ſo ruined, That they are not able to make reall and ready pament of the aforeſaid ſummes impoſed upon them for the Maintenance; Therefore untill ſome tryall bee made of their true condition, They have thought fitting to grant ſuſpenſion: Likeas, they hereby do ſuſpend the exaction of the particular ſummes under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written from the Shires and Burghs following, In manner, and conforme to the limitations aftermentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> From the Shirefedome of <hi>Innernes,</hi> 2000. l. From the Shirefdom of <hi>Sutherland,</hi> 200. l. From the Shirefdom of <hi>Nairne,</hi> 315. l. From the Shirefdom of <hi>Elgine,</hi> 1000. l. From the Shirefdom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152355:3"/>of <hi>Aberdene,</hi> 6543. l. From the Shirefdom of <hi>Bamf,</hi> 1431. l. From the Shiref<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Kincardine,</hi> 400. l. From the Sherifdome of <hi>Forfar,</hi> 500. l. From the Sherifdome of <hi>Pearth,</hi> 3000. l. From the Shirefdome of <hi>Sterling,</hi> 1200. l. From the Shirefdom of <hi>Kinroſe</hi> Shire, 72. l. From the Shirefdome of <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bartan,</hi> 633. l. From the Shirefdom of <hi>Argile,</hi> 2907. l. From the Shiref<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Bute,</hi> 459. l. <hi>Item,</hi> for the Burrows, <hi>viz.</hi> From <hi>Pearth,</hi> 500. l. From <hi>Aberdene,</hi> 1260. l. From <hi>Strivling,</hi> 80. l. From <hi>Innernes,</hi> 450. l. From <hi>Bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen,</hi> 120. l. From <hi>Elgine</hi> 80. l. From <hi>Dumbartan,</hi> 162. l.From <hi>Bamf,</hi> 72. l. From <hi>Rotheſay,</hi> 60. l. From <hi>Culane,</hi> 27. l. From. <hi>Nairne,</hi> 36. l. From <hi>Taine,</hi> 45. l. From <hi>Forfar,</hi> 27. l. From <hi>Forres,</hi> 54. l. From <hi>Dornoch,</hi> 18. l.</p>
            <p>Of the which ſums immediatly abovewritten hereby ſuſpended, It is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That the Generall Commiſſar or his Deputes, ſhall ſute no exaction nor payment before the tenth of May next to come for ſuch Shires and Burrows as are beſouth the water of Dee, and the tenth day of June next for the Shires and Burrows benorth the water of Dee, Betwixt and the which time the Shires and Burghs who have not already taken out Commiſſions, are appointed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to take out Commiſſions from the Parliament, or any Committee eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished or to be eſtabliſhed by them, for cognition of the loſſes direct to ſuch as they reſpectively ſhall nominate to try and report; That the Lands and Burghs are burnt and ſo waſted, that they are totally diſabled to pay rent, or if they be able to pay any rent, that they ſhall pay proportionable Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which ſhall bee reported to the Parliament or their ſaid Committee; That accordingly as they allow or diſallow thereof, the foreſaid ſuſpended part of the Maintenance may be payed or diſcharged. And incaſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or failȝie of the Commſſioners for Shires and Burghs, to take out the ſaids Commiſſions and make the report before the dayes prefixed, The Generall Commiſſioner is hereby warranted to charge them for the whole Mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, without conſideration of the forefaid ſuſpenſion: And for the greater evidence herein, It is ordained, that betwixt and the firſt of April next to come, the valuers of theſe Shires, whereof any part of the Maintenance is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſuſpended, Shall deliver to the ſaid Generall Commiſſar, or any Collector whom he ſhall appoint in each Shire <hi>reſpectivé,</hi> a particular liſt and accompt of theſe Lands, whereupon that part of the Maintenance preſently payable without ſuſpenſion is impoſed; With certification to the ſaids valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in caſe of failȝie of performance hereof before the ſaid day, They ſhall be ſubject in payment of that part of the Maintenance, which is payable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuſpenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> It is ordained, That the Moneths Maintenance payable betwixt the tenth of Februar laſt by paſt, and the tenth of March next to come, Shall be really payed, without any deduction for Quarterings in that time, But that the Quarterings of the new modelled Army and no others disbanded, ſhall be allowed in the firſt end of the Maintenance for the ſubſequent Moneths after the ſaid tenth day of March, and that the ſame ſhall bee deduced and discoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Generall Commiſſar to the Heritors, Fewars, or Liferenters of the firſt of their Maintenance, payable by them <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> after the ſaid tenth day of March, and thereafter to bee charged by the ſaid Generall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſar
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152355:3"/>upon the Regiment accounts, for the Moneths ſubſequent to the ſaid tenth day of March: It is alwayes provided, That theſe Quarterings ſhall be proven and inſtructed, conforme to the Acts of Parliament made or to be made thereanent.</p>
            <p>Further, It is enacted, ſtatute, and ordained, That every debter ſhall have retention from the Creditor of the quantity of one and a halfe of each eight payable for anualrent; So that the debter ſhall onely be lyable in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſix and an halfe of anualrent of ilk hundreth of Stock, and that from the terme and time of Lambmeſſe, 1646. To the terme of Lambmeſſe next to come, 1647. And ſo forth proportionably thence to the laſt day of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber next thereafter following<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> With this declaration and proviſion alwayes, That no Perſon Debter whatſoever, ſhall have the foreſaid benefit of retenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who ſhal not pay his anualrent to the Creditor within the ſpace of ane year out run, after that ane preceding yeares anualrent is fully reſtand awand unpayed: And it is declared hereby, That whatſomever Debter hath beene payed their anualrents at eight <hi>per centum</hi> before the date hereof, at the feaſts of Martimeſſe, or Candlemeſſe now laſt by paſt, Shall have deduction of the Creditor in their next tearmes anualrent, of ſo much as is ordained by this preſent Act to be deduced from Lambmeſſe laſt bygone, to the ſaid time of the payment of the ſaid anualrent: And it is alſo hereby ſpecially provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, That whatſoever Creditor ſhall take hereafter, Band, Promiſe, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from his Debter, for payment to him of the haill anualrent at eight <hi>per centum,</hi> without retention or allowance of the ſaid deduction of the ane and a halfe for the hundreth, during the time preſcribed by this Act, Or ſhall not grant the retention foreſaid, Shall bee conveened and cenſured as ane uſurer, notwithſtanding of any ſuch paction by word or Writ.</p>
            <p>And ſicklike, It is Declared, Statute, and Ordained, That no retention of this preſent Maintenance ſhall be granted for any Debts, Cauſe, or Occaſion whatſomer, and that no exemption other nor is abovewritten for burnt or waſted Lands as is formerly expreſt, ſhall be granted from this preſent Act and Ordinance to any Perſon or Perſons; Except onely for Lands, Rents, Anualrents, and other duties mortified to Colledges, Schooles, Hoſpitalls, Miniſters and Schoolemaſters Stipends, and for upholding Kirks and Bridges; But that all other Heritors, Liferenters, Takſmen, Titulars, Proper-Wodſetters, Penſioners, Conjunctfiers, Ladytercers, and others ſubject to the valuation within Shires and Burghs, ſhall bee lyable to their proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable part of this Maintenance, conforme to the Act already made hereanent in this Seſſion of Parliament, of the date the tenth day of December laſt by paſt; And that the Lands and Teinds ſhall pay as they lye locally in Shires or Burghs, Conforme to the Act of convention for the Loane and Taxt, and former Act of Maintenance.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Where there is any wrong done in valuation, The ſaids Eſtates appoints the valuers of each Shire or <hi>Quorum</hi> thereof, or of ſo many as are on life, and not cenſurable by the Act of Parliament anent the Claſſes, To meet and rectifie the ſame at any time and place as they ſhall appoint: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring alwayes, That this warrand for a new valuation ſhall be no hinderance
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152355:4"/>nor diminution to the Maintenance preſently impoſed: and where there is not a full <hi>Quorum</hi> the valuers on life and not cenſurable, That the number bee ſupplied by the Parliament or Committee of Eſtates; And for the Burrows part, it ſhall be rectified and changed according as their Taxt roll ſhall bee altered, there being no diminution of the totall ſumme: And further, It is ordained, That no ſuſpenſion bee granted without conſignation, as is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Act of Maintenance of the 27 of Februar, 1645. And that all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritours within Burghs, and Pendicles and Liberties thereof (including for <hi>Edinburgh</hi> Pendicles thereof, the Houſes, Tenements and Yeards, in <hi>Leith, Cannnogate,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſance,</hi> Whereof the Town is either Proprietors, or Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, and for the other Burrows all that hath beene in uſe to bee Taxt with them) Shall contribute with them for payment of the Maintenance, conform to thir two clauſes of the ſaid Act, which are holden as inſert, and repeated in this preſent Act; But prejudice of the Lords of Seſſion their Priviledges, conforme to the former Acts of Maintenance: And ordaines this preſent Act to bee Printed: As alſo, Ordaines the foreſaid Act of the convention of Eſtates, anent the Loane and Taxt to bee reprinted.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Alex. Gibſone Cler. Regiſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of_the_Convention_of_Estates">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152355:4"/>
            <head>Act of the Convention of <hi>Estates,</hi> Holden at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the fifteenth of Auguſt, <hi>1643.</hi> for the Loane and Taxt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſameikle as the Kings Majeſtie and Eſtates of this Realm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the late Parliament, taking to their Conſideration the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in Ireland, and danger upon that occaſion threatned againſt the Proteſtant Religion, Did thereupon, and out of their affection to the Kingdome of England, make offer to the ſaid Kingdom of a ſupply of ten thouſand men from this Kingdome, for ſuppreſſing of that Rebellion, To be entertained by the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of England<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to the Capitulation made thereanent by the Commiſſioners ſent from the Parliament of this Kingdome, With inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſent from the Lords of Privie Councell thereof; And accordingly the ſaid ſupply being put over upon the great Charges of this King dome, ſuch have been the great neceſſities and wants of that Army, as well Officers as Souldiers, not only through default of their ordinary pay, but alſo off victuall in the ſpareſt meaſure, and all other neceſſaries, That the Lords of Privie Councell, unto whom the care of that army was entruſted by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and who did accordingly undertake for the ſame, Have been put to great trouble and charges, both by engaging themſelves, and with them alſo the Commiſſioners for the peace and common burdens, As alſo by their joint invitation of the well-affected ſubjects of this kingdome to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſums of money for entertainment of that Army, and payment of the arreares thereof, which they are obliged to pay with the ordinary anuall rent; And howſoever conſiderable ſums have been by their painfull onde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours received, Notwithſtanding, ſuch have been the preſſing miſeries of that Army, in regard of the unhappy diſtractions in England, diſabling the Parliament thereof, according to their obligement to entertian them, as they have expreſt in their ſeverall Declarations ſent to the Lords of His Majeſties Privie Councel; And ſuch have been the difficulties occurring to the ſaids Lords of Privie Councell, Commiſſioners of Peace, and common burdens, touching the farther entertainment of that Army, which they found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them any longer to undergo, as they were moved from their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to this Majeſties ſervice, and ſenſe of the diſtreſſe of their brethren; For this and other the like extreme exigency, nearly importing the good of this Kingdom, to call this Convention of Eſtates, by whoſe authority they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152355:5"/>might more warrantably proceed in matters of ſo great importance: And the ſaids Eſtates having accordingly taken to their conſideration the condition of the ſaid Army, and the whole courſe and procedure concerning the ſame, as is before expreſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore, and for divers other conſiderations moving the ſaids Eſtates, they have thought fit, ſtatute and ordained, Like as by thir preſents they ſtatute and ordaine, The ſumme of twelve hundred thouſand marks Scots money, together with the ſum of one hundred thouſand marks money fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as allowance for charges of ingathering of the ſame, to Collectors, Clerks, and others neceſſary members, and for allowance of exemptions for mortifications, and the Lord Chancellour and fifteen ordinary Lords of the Seſſion, perſons exeemed, as is after ſpecified, To be uplifted by way of Loane, out of the ſeverall Sherifdomes and Burrows of this Kingdome, in manner as is after divided: <hi>viz.</hi> The ſaids Burrowes one ſixth part of the principall ſumme, extending to 200000. marks, and the ſeverall Sherif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this Kingdome to pay the remanent of the ſaids ſums, conform to a particular roll made and ſet down thereanent, and ſubſcribed in preſence of the ſaids Eſtates by the Lord Chancellour, to remain in Record in the bookes of Convention and Collection; Which whole ſums of money to be lent, as ſaid is, as well to Burgh as landward, ſhall be delivered to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, and others having power from the ſaids Eſtates, betwixt the date hereof, and the ſecond day of February next to come 1644. yeares.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the ſummes of money preſently to be lent, are not to be inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered aff the ſhires, as taxations have been, or by the diviſions of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralities and Spiritualities, But rather is thought fit that the ſame may be uplifted out of the lands, teinds, and others, as they lie locally in every She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifdome promiſcuouſly, conforme to the ſaid roll ſubſcribed as ſaid is.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is thought neceſſary that ſeverall Sub-collectors be appointed through the whole Kingdome, in ilk ſhire or ſhires one or more; Which Sub-collector or Collectors, ſo to be appointed, ſhall be charged with the whole ſums of moneyes to be lent by the ſhire or ſhires where he or they ſhall be Collector.</p>
            <p>And to the effect the ſaids Sub-collectors may have letters of relief againſt the ſeverall perſons to be contained and ſet downe in the Rolls after-mentioned:</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſaids Eſtates have nominate the perſons following: <hi>viz.</hi> For the Sherifdome of Orkney, <hi>Thomas Buchanan</hi> of Sound, Sherif of Orkney, and <hi>Patrick Smith</hi> of Braco, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the reſt of the Shire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>Jamis Baikie</hi> of Tankernes, <hi>Adam Ballinden</hi> of Stanehouſe, <hi>James Mudie</hi> of Melſetter, <hi>Patrick Balfour</hi> of Feary, <hi>Edward Sinclar</hi> of Gyre.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdomes of Innernes and Cromertie, Sir <hi>John Mackenȝie</hi> of Tarbet, Maſter <hi>Alexander Mackenȝie</hi> of Kilcowie, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>Walter Innes</hi> of Innerbraiky, <hi>Coline Mackenȝie</hi> of Kincraig, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Monro</hi> of Obſtail, <hi>Alexander Dumbar</hi> of Bennetsfield, <hi>Robert Innes</hi> of Roskeene, <hi>Hugh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152355:5"/>Fraſer</hi> of Belladrum, <hi>John Grant</hi> of Lurgie, <hi>John Maccleud</hi> of Dunevegan, <hi>Neil Macneil</hi> of Baro, Sir <hi>James Fraſer</hi> of Bray, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Roſſe</hi> of Pitca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, <hi>Walter Roſſe</hi> of Kindroſſe, <hi>Thomas Roſſe</hi> of Prieſthill.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Caitnes, Sir <hi>James Sinclar</hi> of Murtill, <hi>David Sinclar</hi> of Dun, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the Shire to make choice of their own Conveeners) <hi>James Sutherland</hi> of Forſe, <hi>David Cogle</hi> of that Ilk, <hi>John Sinclar</hi> of Scrabſter, <hi>James Sinclar</hi> of Brymnes, <hi>John Innes</hi> of Stuiſter.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Sutherland, Sir <hi>Alexander Sutherland</hi> of Duffus, <hi>Robert Murray</hi> of Pulroſſie, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the ſhire to make choice of their Conveeners) <hi>Robert Gray</hi> of Creich, <hi>Walter Murray</hi> of Pitgourdie, <hi>Alexander Gordoun</hi> of Carrell, <hi>Hugh Mackye</hi> of Skowrie, <hi>Robert Gray</hi> of Boltoun.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Nairn, <hi>George Campbel</hi> brother to the Laird of Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, <hi>William Dollace</hi> of Contra, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after the reſt of the ſhire to make choice of their own Conveeners) <hi>Hugh Roſſe</hi> of Kilraok, <hi>Alexander Broddie</hi> of Lethin, <hi>John Grant</hi> of Moynes, <hi>William Roſſe</hi> of Clava, <hi>Thomas Dumbar</hi> Tutor of Grange, <hi>Patrick Paplay</hi> of Broomhill.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdom of Elgin, Sir <hi>Robert Gordoun</hi> of that Ilk, Sir <hi>Robert Innes</hi> of that Ilk, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter the reſt of the Shire to make choice of their own Conveeners) Sir <hi>Alexander Sutherland</hi> of Duffus, Maſter <hi>John Hay</hi> Proveſt of Elgin, <hi>Alexander Dumbar</hi> of Weſtfield, <hi>Ninian Dumbar</hi> of Grangehill, <hi>James Gram</hi> of Frewchie, <hi>John Cuming</hi> of Racowcas.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Aberdeen, the Lairds of Drum and Phillorth to be Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter thoſe of the Shire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>Robert Farquhareſon</hi> of Innercald, <hi>John Irwing</hi> of Beltie, <hi>Alexander Straquhan</hi> of Glenkendie, Sir <hi>William Forbes</hi> of Craigievar, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Davidſon</hi> of Cairnie, Sir <hi>Gilbert Meinȝies</hi> of Pitfodells <hi>Thomas Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skine</hi> of Pittoddrie, M. <hi>Robert Farquhare</hi> of Munie, M. <hi>Robert Gordoun</hi> of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurg <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Gordoun</hi> of Cokclarochie, <hi>John Owdnie</hi> of that Ilk, <hi>James Hay</hi> of Muryfauld, <hi>Robert Irwing</hi> of Fedret, <hi>William Keith</hi> of Clakriach.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Bamffe, <hi>Alexander Ogilvie</hi> Kempcarne, <hi>Thomas Abercrumbie</hi> of Skeith, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter thoſe of the Shire to chooſe their own Conveeners) <hi>James Stewart</hi> of Ordeins, <hi>Walter Grant</hi> of Mellers, <hi>Alexander Ogilvie</hi> of Knok, <hi>James Barclay</hi> of Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minnettie, <hi>Alexander Leſly</hi> of Auchindoun, <hi>John Grant</hi> younger of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lindalloch.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Kincardin, Sir <hi>Alexander Falconer</hi> younger fiar of Hackerton, Sir <hi>Alexander Carnegie</hi> of Pittaro, Conveeners for the firſt meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (and thereafter thoſe of the Shires to make choiſe of their own Conveen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) Sir <hi>Robert Grahame</hi> of Morphie, Six <hi>Gilbert Ramſay</hi> of Balmain, <hi>Robert Keith</hi> of Whiterigs, Sheriffe depute of Kincardin, <hi>Patrick Falconer</hi> of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>John Barcley</hi> of Johnſton, <hi>John Falconer</hi> fiar of Newton.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Forfar, <hi>Robert Arbuthnet</hi> of Findowry, Sir <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Carnegie</hi> of Ballnamoon, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152355:6"/>the reſt of the Shire to make choiſe of their own Conveeners) <hi>John Lord Loure, Peter Young</hi> of Seaton, <hi>William Ruthven</hi> Gairn, M. <hi>James Durhame</hi> of Pitcairo, <hi>James Vicount</hi> of Dudop, <hi>William Durhame</hi> elder of Grange, M. <hi>William Durhame</hi> of Omaquhie, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Maxwell</hi> of Telin, <hi>James</hi> Lord Couper, <hi>James Crichton</hi> of Ruthven, Sir <hi>William Blair</hi> of Bagillo <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Lyon</hi> of Brigton, <hi>Henry Mauld</hi> of Melgume, <hi>Thomas Fothringham</hi> of Dununne.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Perth, The Lairds of Inſhbrakie, and Inſhture, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to make choiſe amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) <hi>Thomas Blair</hi> of Baltheyok, Sir <hi>Thomas Ruthven</hi> of Frieland, <hi>John Oliphant</hi> of Bachilron, <hi>Peter Hay</hi> of Leyis, Six <hi>Patrick Ogilvie</hi> of Inſhmartin, Sir <hi>Robert Campbell</hi> of Glennorquhie, <hi>Alexander Menȝies</hi> of Comrie, <hi>Patrick Ratra</hi> of Cuaighall, <hi>Gilbert Campbell</hi> of Keithik, <hi>John Blair</hi> of Ardblair, M. <hi>Patrick Murray</hi> fiar of Ochtertyre, <hi>James Drumond</hi> of Milnab, Sir <hi>John Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> of Glenegies, <hi>William Sterling</hi> elder of Auchyle.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Fyfe and Kinros, the Lairds of Scotſcraig, and Danemilne to be Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to make choiſe among themſelves) Sir <hi>James Halket</hi> fiar of Pitfirrane, <hi>William Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeth</hi> of Randefoord, <hi>John Henderſon</hi> of Fordell, <hi>Robert Dempſter</hi> of Balbougie, Sir <hi>George Hammiltoun</hi> of Blaikburn, Sir <hi>John Weymes</hi> of Boegy, M. <hi>Robert Ayton</hi> of Inſhdairnie, Sir <hi>Andrew Skeen</hi> of Halyeardis, Sir <hi>James Arnot</hi> of Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Sir <hi>John Ayton</hi> of that Ilk, <hi>James Maegill</hi> of Rankelour elder, <hi>George Hay</hi> fiar of Nachtoun, Sir <hi>Thomas Myreton</hi> of Cambo, M. <hi>James Reid</hi> of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lethie, <hi>William Forbes</hi> younger of Rires, Sir <hi>William Douglas</hi> of Kirknes, and <hi>David Balfour</hi> of Ballo.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Sterling, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Murray</hi> of Polmaes <hi>John Rollok</hi> of Bannokburn, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter the reſt of the Shire to make choice of their own Conveeners, fir <hi>Thomas Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colſon</hi> of Carnok, <hi>William Levingſtone</hi> of Waſtquarter, <hi>William Roſſe</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>John Sterling</hi> of Harbertſhire, ſir <hi>James Levingſton</hi> of Bancloth, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Stirling</hi> of Glorat, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Kinked</hi> of Archinreach, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Hamiltoun</hi> of Baldoure, <hi>William Blair</hi> of Fenik, <hi>John Lennox</hi> of Cairne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhokle, M. <hi>William Cunningham</hi> ok Balindalloch, M. <hi>Robert Naper</hi> of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crewch, <hi>James Stirling</hi> of Balwill, <hi>Alexander Cunningham</hi> of Baquhane.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Clakmannan, Sir <hi>Charles Erskin</hi> of Bandeth, Sir <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> of Clakmannan, and Sir <hi>Alexander Shaw</hi> of Sauchie, Convee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice amongſt themſelves, Maſter <hi>Robert Bruce</hi> of Kennet, <hi>James Hadden</hi> of Myreton, <hi>William Graham</hi> of Hilton, <hi>William Reid</hi> of Craigheid.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Edinburgh, Sir <hi>Archibald Johnſtoun</hi> of Wariſton, and the Laird of Libberton, to be Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to chooſe among themſelves, Sir <hi>Patrick Hammiltoun</hi> of little Preſton, Sir <hi>William Scot</hi> of Clerkington, <hi>David Macullo</hi> of Guidtrees, M. <hi>John Inglis</hi> of Nether-Cramond, M. <hi>David Anderſoun</hi> of Hill, M. <hi>John Cant</hi> of Pentland, <hi>Marke Kerſſe</hi> of Cokpen, M. <hi>Samuell Johnſtoun</hi> of Scheans.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Linlithgow, The Lairds of Daundas and Balbachlaw, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice among
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152355:6"/>themſelves, <hi>William Drummond</hi> of Riccarton, Sir <hi>Walter Murray</hi> of Leving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoun, <hi>George Dundas</hi> of Dudingſtoun; Sir <hi>Robert Drummond</hi> of Medop, M. <hi>George Dundas</hi> of Maner, M. <hi>James Hamiltoun</hi> of Weſt-port, <hi>Samuell Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> of Carlowrie.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Hadingtoun, Sir <hi>Patrick Hepburne</hi> of Wachtoun, and Sir <hi>Adam Hepburne</hi> of Humbie, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe among themſelves, M. <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Hepburne</hi> of Smeitoun, <hi>Patrick Inglis</hi> of Eivingſtoun, M. <hi>James Sydſerffe</hi> of Rauchlaw, <hi>John Hepburn</hi> of Craig, M. <hi>Alexander Hay</hi> of Bara, <hi>William Cairnes</hi> of Pilmoore, <hi>George VVood</hi> Neumilnes.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Berwik, The Lairds of Aitoun and Blaikader, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe among themſelves, <hi>George Auchinlek</hi> of Cumledge, <hi>Alexander Home</hi> of Reſtoun, <hi>Alexander Home</hi> of Rollandſtone, <hi>James Home</hi> of Caſtell-law, M. <hi>Alexander Home</hi> of Saint Leonards, M. <hi>George Home</hi> of Kymergem, <hi>William Home</hi> of Linthill.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Roxburgh, The Lairds of Stobbs and Cavers, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice amongſt themſelves. Sir <hi>Walter Riddell</hi> of that ilk, Maſter <hi>George Douglas</hi> of Bonne-Jedburgh, <hi>John Ker</hi> of Lochtour, <hi>Robert Pringle</hi> of Stichell, <hi>John Scot</hi> of Gorranberrie, <hi>Walter Scot</hi> Gaudielands, M. <hi>Gilbert Ellot</hi> of Craig end, <hi>James Pringle</hi> of Buckholme, <hi>John Scot</hi> of Heidſhaw, <hi>John Rutherfoord</hi> of Capehope, <hi>Robert Landlans</hi> of that ilk, <hi>Walter Riddell</hi> portioner of Bewley, <hi>Andrew Bell</hi> of Mow, <hi>Andrew Ker</hi> of Sinles.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Selkirk, The Lairds of Harden and Whitſleid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves, <hi>James Pringle</hi> of Torwoodlie, <hi>James Pringle</hi> of Whitebank, <hi>Neil Scot</hi> of Gallaſcheills, <hi>William Scot</hi> of New-wark, <hi>Robert Scot</hi> of Hartwoodmyres, <hi>Robert Scot</hi> of Bowhill, <hi>Francis Scot</hi> of Synton.</p>
            <p>For the Sherifdome of Peibles, Sir <hi>Alexander Murray</hi> of Blakbarronie, Sir <hi>David Murray</hi> of Stonehope, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to make choice among themſelves, Sir <hi>Michael Naeſmith</hi> of Poſſo, M. <hi>James Lawſon</hi> of Cairnmure, <hi>Robert Hunter</hi> of Polmood, <hi>Andrew Hay</hi> of Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, <hi>William Govan</hi> of Cardrona.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Lanerk, The Lairds of Belſtane, and Dalſerff, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Sir <hi>James Hamiltoun</hi> of Fingletoun, <hi>Edward Hamiltoun</hi> of Sillertonhill, <hi>Gavin Hamiltoun</hi> of Raploch, <hi>William Baillie</hi> of Carphin, <hi>Robert Hamiltoun</hi> of Aikinheid, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Crafurd</hi> of Kibbers, <hi>Andrew Hamiltoun</hi> portioner of Overtoun, Sir <hi>William Baillie</hi> of Laminton, Sir <hi>William Carmichell</hi> fiar of that ilk, <hi>George Weir</hi> of Blaikwood, <hi>John Bannatine</hi> of Corhous, <hi>James Hamiltoun</hi> of Halcraig, <hi>James Winraham</hi> of Wolſtoun, M. <hi>John Carmichell</hi> Commiſſer of Lanerk, <hi>James Hamiltoun</hi> of Sandieholme, <hi>James Hamiltoun</hi> of Boigs.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Air, The Lairds of Rowallan, and the Laird of Corsby, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves, <hi>Hew Campbell</hi> of Ceſnoke, <hi>James Chalmer</hi> of Gadgirth, Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Cochrane</hi> of Coudoun, <hi>Allan Cathcart</hi> younger of Cairnehill, <hi>Robert Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quhar</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152355:7"/>of Gilmicroft, <hi>Neill Montgomrie</hi> of Langſhaw, <hi>Robert Montgomrie</hi> of Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filheid, <hi>John Crafurd</hi> of Crafurdland, <hi>David Kennedie</hi> elder of Kirkmichell, <hi>Thomas Boyd</hi> of Pankill, <hi>Gabriell Porterfield</hi> of Hapland, <hi>John Cunninghame</hi> of Bordland, <hi>Henry Kelſo</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>John Mac-Alexander</hi> of Corſclayes, <hi>John Macclevin</hi> of Grimmet, M. <hi>Adam Cunningham</hi> of Priviks.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Wigtoun and Stewartry of Kirkcudbright, The Laird of Garthland, and the young Sheriffe of Galloway, Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice among themſelves, Sir <hi>Patrick Makgie</hi> of Large, <hi>John Makgie</hi> of Balmagie, <hi>William Grierſon</hi> of Bargaltoun, <hi>Alexander Gordoun,</hi> of Erleſtoun, <hi>James Roſſe</hi> of Banneill, <hi>John Mackulloth</hi> of Mertoun, <hi>John Fullerton</hi> of Carletoun, <hi>Robert Mackullo</hi> of Drummorell, <hi>George Glendoning</hi> of Mochrumi, <hi>VVilliam Gordoun</hi> of Crachlaw, <hi>Uchtry Mackdowgall</hi> of French, <hi>Patrick Agnew</hi> of Sewchram, <hi>Richard Mure</hi> of Caſſincarthy, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Makclellan</hi> of Colin, <hi>Patrick Agnew</hi> of Barneweil, <hi>Iohn Stewart</hi> of Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belly, <hi>VVilliam Glendoning</hi> Proveſt of Kirkudbright, <hi>Iames Lafreis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Drumfreis, The Laird of Lag and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> Conveeners for the firſt meeting, and thereafter to make choice among themſelves, M. <hi>George Douglas</hi> of Pymurie, <hi>Thomas Ferguſon</hi> of Caitloch, <hi>Iohn Creightoun</hi> of Crafoord John, <hi>James Douglas</hi> of Mortoun, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Maxwell</hi> of Steilſtoun, <hi>Iohn Grierſon</hi> of Chappell, <hi>Hugh Charters</hi> of Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corſe, <hi>Alexander Ferguſon</hi> of Ile, <hi>James Douglas</hi> of Mouſewall, <hi>Robert Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of Douchra, <hi>Iames Iohnſtoun</hi> of Corheid, <hi>Andrew Iohnſtoun</hi> of Locherby, <hi>Matthew VVilſon</hi> of Greenhill, <hi>Francis Scot</hi> of Cartertoun, <hi>Iohn Kennedie</hi> of Halklaithes, <hi>Archbald Dowglas</hi> of Dronock.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Renfrew, the Laird of Grenock, and <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to meet and chooſe amongſt themſelves) Sir <hi>Lodowick Houſtoun</hi> of that ilk, <hi>Iohn Birſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> of Biſhoptoun, <hi>Alexander Portetfield</hi> of that ilk, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Pook</hi> elder of that ilk, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Caldwall</hi> of that ilk, <hi>Iohn Maxwell</hi> of Southbarre, <hi>Iames Orr</hi> of Langfillie.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Dumbartan, the Laird of Fulwood, Conveener for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves) <hi>VValter Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaula</hi> of Ardincaple, <hi>Iohn Naper</hi> of Kilmahew, <hi>Robert Hall</hi> of Fulbarre, <hi>Robert Cochrane</hi> of Bellarmik, <hi>
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Carſhore</hi> of that ilk, <hi>Iohn Colquhone</hi> of Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madymne, <hi>Hugh Craford</hi> of Claverhill, <hi>Iohn Denneſtoun</hi> of Dalquharrie.</p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Argyle, the Lairds of Glenurquhie, and Auchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brek, Conveeners for the firſt meeting (and thereafter to chooſe amongſt themſelves) <hi>Iames Campbell</hi> of Arkinelies, <hi>Archbald Campbell</hi> of Kilmure, Sir <hi>Lachlane Makclene</hi> of Dowart, <hi>Archbald Campbell</hi> of Dunſtaffnik, Sheriffe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of Argyle, <hi>George Campbell, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Hector Makneil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Sheriffdome of Bute, the Laird of Skelmorlie, Conveener for the firſt meeting, Sir <hi>Iames Stuart</hi> of Kirktowne, <hi>Ninian Stuart</hi> of Kilcatton, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Stuart</hi> elder of Aſhcock, <hi>Hector Bannatyne</hi> of Kaynes, <hi>Iohn Stuart</hi> of Aliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Neil Makneil</hi> of Kilmore, <hi>Iohn Campbell</hi> ſometime Proveſt of Rothſay.</p>
            <p>Who ſhall conveene with the whole Heritours, Life-renters, Takſmen,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152355:7"/>Titulars, proper Wad-ſetters, Penſioners, Conjunctfiers, Lady tercers, and others, within ilk one of their ſaids Sheriffdomes <hi>respectivè,</hi> Or at leaſt with ſo many of the ſaids perſons as ſhall bee conveened for the time, upon the firſt Tueſday of October next, as the firſt day of their meeting appointed for the whole Shires of the Kingdome: And to the effect the ſame may be known to the whole lieges:</p>
            <p>It is ordained, that the Conveener or Conveeners of the ſhires before named, ſhall cauſe intimate the ſaid meeting at the Market croſſe of the head Burgh of the ſhire with all convenient diligence, and at every Pariſh Kirk thereof, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after Divine Service, upon any Sunday preceding the 22. day of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember next, and to meet ilk ſhire at the places following, <hi>viz.</hi> The Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Orkney at the town of Kirkwall, the Sheriffdome of Caitnes at the town of Thurſay, the Sheriffdome of Sutherland at the towne of Dornoch, the Sheriffdomes of Innernes and Cromertie at the Burgh of Innernes, the Sheriffdome of Narn at the Burgh of Narn, the Sheriffdome of Elgin at the Burgh of Elgin, the Sheriffdome of Bamf at the Burgh of Bamf, the Sheriff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Aberdene at the Burgh of Aberdene, the Sheriffdome of Kincardine at the towne of Stanehyve, the Sheriffdome of Forfar at the Burgh of Forfar, the Sheriffdome of Perth at the Burgh of Perth, the Sheriffdomes of Fife and Kinros at the Burgh of Cowper, the Sheriffdome of Clakmannan, at the town of Clakmannan, the Sheriffdome of Sterling at the Burgh of Sterling, the Sheriffdome of Renfrew at the Burgh of Renfrew, the Sheriffdome of Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bartan at the Burgh of Dumbartan, the Sheriffdome of Argyle at the Burgh of Innerara, the Sheriffdome of Bute at the Burgh of Rotheſay, the Sheriffdome of Lanerk at the Burgh of Lanerk, the Sheriffdome of Air at the Burgh of Air, the Sheriffdome of Wigtoun and Stuartrie of Kircudbright at the Burgh of Wigtoun, the Sheriffdome of Dumfreis at the Burgh of Dumfreis, the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffdome of Roxburgh at the Burgh of Jedburgh, the Sheriffdome of Selkirk at the Burgh of Selkirk, the Sheriffdome of Peibles at the Burgh of Peibles, the Sheriffdome of Berwick at the towne of Duns, the Sheriffdome of Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingtoun at the Burgh of Haddingtoun, the Sheriffdome of Edinburgh at the Burgh of Edinburgh, the Sheriffdome of Linlithgow at the Burgh of Linlith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow. And there the ſaids Conveeners, or any of them, with ſuch other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners as ſhall be conveened for the time, ſhall cauſe call by name and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, the Heritours, Live-renters, Titulars, Takſmen of teinds, proper Wad-ſetters, Penſioners, Ladie tercers, and others within the ſaids Sheriffdomes, who bruike any benefit to landward, whereby any profit or commoditie ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, And by conſent of them, or moſt part of them conveened for the time, ſhall make choice of a ſelect number of perſons, to bee joyned with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids Commiſſioners, choſen by the Convention, to the number of eight per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in the foreſaids ſhires where there are ſixteen choſen by the Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the number of three perſons in the reſt of the ſhires, being judicious, conſciencious, and underſtanding men, who ſhall (as well theſe nominate as thoſe to be elected) give their ſolemne oathes judicially at their firſt meeting, in preſence of the ſaid Conveener or Conveeners, who are hereby authorized to take their oaths, to doe uprightly and impartially, according to their beſt knowledge and information in the particulars following.</p>
            <p>With power to the ſaids Commiſſioners, or moſt part of them conveened for the time, to make choice of a Clerk for writing and forming of the rolls after
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152355:8"/>ſpecified, and doing every other thing incumbent to the charge after following.</p>
            <p>Which Commiſſioners ſo nominate and elected, ſhall uſe all lawfull meanes, according to the time, and if need bee, ſhall direct out ſummons at their own inſtances againſt any perſon or perſons within the ſaid ſhire, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere before them, and give them information upon oath or other wayes, with certification of a pecuniall ſumme, not exceeding fourtie pounds <hi>toties quoties,</hi> in caſe of contempt and refuſall.</p>
            <p>And with power to the ſaids Commiſſioners, to uſe all other legall way to informe themſelves of the juſt and true worth of every perſon or perſons thir preſent years rent of this cropt and year 1643. to landward, as well of lands and teinds, as of any other thing whereby yearly profit and commodity ariſeth.</p>
            <p>And that the worth of every perſon or perſons, their lands, teinds and other commodities, where greſſums and entereſſe have been payd, be valued and ſet downe, not only as they pay to the Heritors, Liferenters, and other their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, but as the ſame are worth, and may pay preſently, without reſpect of greſſums or entereſſe, and to divide the ſaids Rolls in particular Pariſhes, by making a Roll for every ſelverall Pariſh within the ſaid Shire; Which Roll ſhall containe every particular Perſons name, ſurname, and deſignation, with their ſaids years Rent, and Commodity within the ſaid Pariſh, whether in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, Money, or other Commodities.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid Victuall and Commodities to be converted into money by the ſaids Commiſſioners, upon their former Oathes, according as in every Pariſh the prices of ſelverall ſpaces of Victuall and Commodities ſhall rule for the time; deducing aff the ſaids Rents and Commodities what is paid forth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to Miniſters, School-maſters, Superiors, Takſmen, Life-renters, Colledges, and Hoſpitals; Which deduction aff the ſaids Life-renters, Takſmen and Superiours, ſhall be charged upon the ſaids Life-renters, Takſmen and Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, by Articles apart, together with any other Rent, any they have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <p>As alſo becauſe it is neceſſary to be known what the ſaid deductions of Miniſters and School-maſters ſtipends and exemptions extends to, It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and ordained, that at the end of every one of the ſaids Rolls, Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles ſhall be ſet downe thereof: <hi>viz.</hi> One for the ſaids deductions of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and School-maſters ſtipends, and another for the ſaids exemptions of every Pariſh.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe appointed, that in the ſetting down of the ſaids Rols, this years conſtant land rent ſhall be diſtinguiſhed from the other caſuall rent, whereby yearly profit and commodity ariſeth.</p>
            <p>And for performing and perfecting of the ſaids Rolls, the ſaids Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners and others foreſaids, ſhall appoint their ſeveral diets of meeting, betwixt the firſt Tueſday of October next to come, and the fifteenth day of Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereafter, which is appointed to be the laſt day peremptorily for perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and delivering of the ſaids Rols.</p>
            <p>And which rols ſo perfected and concluded, ſhall be ſubſcribed by the ſaids perſons nominate and to be elected as ſaid is, or moſt part thereof conveened for the time, and which particular rolls of every particular Perſon of every Pariſh, ſhall be kept <hi>in retentis</hi> within the ſaid Shire in ſome truſty perſon or perſons hands, not to be made publick, nor ſhown, except to the Collector of the ſaid Pariſh, who muſt make uſe thereof, in uplifting of the ſums due to be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152355:8"/>paid by the ſaid Pariſh, unleſſe upon occaſion of queſtion betwixt party and party, or betwixt the ſaid Collector and party.</p>
            <p>And after perfecting of the which rolls the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall draw up aff the ſaids particular rolls of Pariſhes a generall roll containing as many ſeverall Articles as there are ſelverall Pariſhes or parcels of Pariſhes (if any be divided within ſeverall Shires) which Articles ſhall be ſet downe in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following: <hi>viz. A. B.</hi> for himſelf and remanent Heritours, Life-renters, and others within the Pariſh of <hi>D.</hi> for their proper rent of the ſaid Pariſh, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to the ſum of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> (victuall and others commodities being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into money) their part of the ſaid Loane extends to <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſo forth, throughout the reſt of the whole Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>In the which roll there muſt be ſet down <hi>in cumulo</hi> the deductions of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and School-maſters ſtipends (if any be) in an Article.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> in another Article mortified and excemed rents, if any be.</p>
            <p>And ſicklike in ſetting down of the ſaid Article for the whole Pariſh, it muſt be diſtinguiſhed what thereof is conſtant land rent, and what is caſuall rent.</p>
            <p>Which generall rolls, containing onely an Article for every Pariſh within ilk Shire, being ſo ſet downe and ſubſcribed by the Commiſſioners, or moſt part thereof conveened for the time, and containing the ſaid Articles of dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and exemptions, and diſtinctions, in maner foreſaid, ſhall be delivered by the ſaids Commiſſioners, or their Clerk, to the Sub-collectors of the ſaid Shire appointed, or to bee appointed for that effect, betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of November next to come, and by the ſaid Sub-collector, to the Clerk of the ſaid collection, that the ſame may bee a ground and warrand for raiſing of Letters thereupon againſt the ſaids Collectors of ſeverall Pariſhes, or perſons nominate in the ſaids generall rolls for every Pariſh.</p>
            <p>And if any of the ſaids Commiſſioners hereby nominate, and to bee elected for ſetting down of the ſaid roll, ſhall refuſe to accept, or be negligent in doing their faithfull diligence therein; It is herefore ſtatute and ordained, that letters ſhall bee direct to meſſengers of armes to command and charge every one of the foreſaids perſons to accept the ſaid Commiſſion within 24. hours after they be charged, and to do their exact diligence therein untill the finall cloſe thereof, and to deliver the ſaids rolls ſubſcribed by the betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of November next to come, under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c. And if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheat, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And incaſe the ſaids ſtent rolls ſhall not be ſet downe, perfected, ſubſcribed, and delivered betwixt and the ſaid 15 day of November next to come; In that caſe letters ſhall be direct againſt the ſaids Commiſſioners nominate and to be elected, to pay the whole ſums of money to bee lent by the ſaid ſhire, which Commiſſioners are ordained hereby to be the firſt payers thereof, in caſe they ſhall refuſe or failȝie to ſet down, perfect, and deliver the ſaids rolls betwixt and the ſaid 15. day of November next to come, under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c. and if they failȝie to denounce and eſcheat, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby declared, that in the caſe foreſaid of their neglect, as ſaid is, and of their firſt payment of the ſumme to be lent by the ſaid ſhire, In that caſe, and after payment thereof made by them, they ſhall have letters of relief againſt the whole Heritours, Life-renters, and others of the ſaid Sheriffdome, conforme to the roll when it ſhall be made up and ſubſcribed by them, or moſt part of them, as ſaid is.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152355:9"/>
            <p> It is hereby alſo declared, that it ſhall be lawfull and leiſome to every perſon or perſons, (excepting the Commiſſioners nominate, and to be elected as ſaid is) intereſt in the ſums to be lent by the ſaid ſhire, who cannot conveniently come to the ſaids meetings, to ſend their Procurators authorized by them in writ, who ſhall have ſuch like power in doing every thing as they might doe themſelves, if they were perſonally preſent.</p>
            <p>It is hereby likewiſe declared, that incaſe any of the Heritours, Life-ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Titulers, Takſmen of Teinds, proper Wad-ſetters or others within the ſaid ſhire, ſhall not conveen at the day and dayes appointed, or to be appointed for that effect, it ſhall be leiſome to the ſaids perſons hereby nominate, or moſt part of them conveened for the time, to make and ſet downe the ſaids rolls, perfect, ſubſcribe and deliver the ſame, in manner aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And that the ſums of money ſo to be lent by the ſaids ſhires, may be uplifted and inbrought, It is Statute and Ordained, that letters ſhall bee directed for charging the whole ſub-collectours within ilk ſhire or ſhires, to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole ſums of money, due to be paid by the ſaid ſhires, whereof they are or ſhall be appointed Sub-collectours, conforme to the ſaid roll, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the ſaid Lord Chancellour in preſence of the ſaid Convention, at the ſaid Terme of Candlemas next, under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And for the ſaids Sub-collectours their relief aff the ſhires, It is ſtatute and ordained that letters ſhall bee directed, charging the ſeverall Collectours of every Parochin within the ſaid-ſhire or ſhires, or perſons nominate in the ſaids particular rolls for payment to the ſaid Sub-collectour, or his deputies, of the ſums contained in the ſaids rolls, and that within twenty dayes next after they be charged, if they be within this Kingdom: And if they be without the ſame, by open Proclamation at the Market Croſſe of Edinburgh, Piere arid Shore of Leith, upon threeſcore dayes warning, under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c. And if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheit, and to poynd and diſtrenȝie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And for relief of the ſaid Collectour of every ſeverall parochine or perſons nominate in the ſaids particular rolls, It is hereby ſtatute and ordained, that letters ſhall be directed for payment making to them of the ſums contained in the ſaid particular rolls againſt every particular perſon or perſons contained in the ſaids rolls, within eight dayes after they be charged, if they be within this Kingdome: And if they be without the ſame, by open Proclamation at the Market Croſſe of Edinburgh, Peire and Shoare of Leith, upon 60. dayes warning, under the pain of rebellion, &amp;c. With power to poynd and diſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ȝie their readieſt goods and geire that ſhall be found upon the ground of any of their ſaids lands, who ſhall not timouſly pay, whether the ſaids goods pertain to theſe liable in the ſaid loane or not, which goods being ſo poynded, it ſhall not be neceſſary to carry them to the Market Croſſe of the head Burgh of the ſhire, but onlxy to uſe the ordinary way of poynding and appriſing upon the ground of the ſaids lands, together with the ſumme of twenty markes for ilk hundreth markes failȝie.</p>
            <p>And for inbringing of the Burrowes part of the ſaid loane, Ordains letters to be direct, charging the Proveſt and Bailies of ilk Burgh, to make payment of their part thereof (conforme to one roll to be ſubſcribed by the Clerk of the Burrowes, or conform to the old roll,) To the ſaid Collectour generall, his Deputies and officers in his name, having his power to receive the ſame at the ſaid terme above ſpecified, an if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheat, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152355:9"/>
            <p> And for their relief, that letters be direct, charging the Proveſt, Bailies and Councell within each Burgh to conveen and elect certain perſons to ſtent their neighbours, and the ſaid election being made to charge the perſons elected to accept the charge upon them, in ſetting down the ſaid ſtent upon the ſaids neighbours, and to conveene and ſet the ſame, and to make a ſtent roll there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon as effeires, within twenty foure houres next after the charge, under the pain of rebellion: And if they failȝie, to denounce and eſcheit, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſicklike, the ſaid ſtent roll being made and ſet down as ſaid is, to charge the Burgeſſes, Indwellees, and Inhabitants within each Burgh, to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their part of the ſaid loan to the ſaid Proveſt and Bailies, Conform to the ſaid rol to be given out thereupon, within three dayes next after the charge under the pain of rebellion; and if they failȝie to denounce and eſcheit, &amp;c. And if needs be that the ſaid Proveſt and Bailies poynd and diſtrenȝie as they ſhall think expedient.</p>
            <p>It is alwayes provided, that no perſon whatſoever be ſtented within Burgh, for any lands or poſſeſſions which he hath to landwart.</p>
            <p>It is hereby likewiſe declared, that the charges to be given for payment of the ſaid loane, may be execute as well againſt theſe that are without the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as theſe that are within the Countrey before the ſaid terme of payment, but that the execution of denunciation and poynding ſhall not be execute until the ſaid terme of payment be bygone, and the ſeverall dayes of the charges <hi>reſpectivè</hi> foreſaids be alſo by paſt.</p>
            <p>And in reſpect that the foreſaids whole ſums of money ſo to be lent by the ſaids Shires and Burrowes, Is for relief of the great ſummes of money al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken on, as ſaid is, and to be advanced for ſupply of the ſaid army in Ireland, which ſhould be repayed by the Parliament of England out of the firſt end of the arrears due to that army.</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſaids Eſtates have not onely ratified and approven the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid act of Councell, with concourſe of the ſaids Commiſſioners for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the peace and Commiſſioners of the common burthens, but alſo have of new Statute and Ordained, Like as they be thir preſents Statute and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that aſwel theſe who have already advan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed money or victuall, or who have engaged themſelves for payment of the prices of victuall, money, and other proviſion by warrant of the ſaids Lords of Councell alone, Or by warrant of them joyntly with the ſaids Commiſſioners of peace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon burthens, but alſo the whole foreſaids ſummes (whereof the ſaids for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer advancements are apart) are hereby ordained to be repayed out of the firſt and readieſt of the ſaids arrears, conform to the tennour, and upon the conditions mentioned in the ſaid Act of Councel, with concourſe foreſaid,</p>
            <p>And in caſe the ſame ſhal not be repayed by the Parliament of England, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt and the ſaid ſecond day of February next to come, It is hereby ſtatute &amp; ordained, like as the ſaids Eſtates by thir preſents ſtatutes and ordaines, that the whole foreſaids perſons, who have by warrand foreſaid advanced money, victuall, or other proviſion, to the ſaid Army; preceding the date hereof, conform to the particular count thereof regiſtrate in the books of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the date hereof, ſhall be repayed ilk man of his ſeverall ſums, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the intereſt thereof, conform to the tenour of the foreſaid Acts, and that out of the firſt and readieſt of the ſums of money to be uplifted by vertue of this preſent Act, and that by the Collector, Sub-collector, and others
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152355:10"/>having warrand and power to receive the ſame, betwixt and the laſt day of February next to come.</p>
            <p>So that it ſhall not be leiſome to the ſaids Collectors or others, to diſpoſe upon any of the ſaids moneyes ſo to be lent, without the conſent of thoſe who have lent the ſaid money or victuall, untill they be firſt ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>And in caſe the ſaid Parliament of England ſhall happen not to pay and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the ſaids bygone arreares, at leaſt ſo much thereof as ſhall repay the ſaids ſums ſo to be lent, as ſaid is, betwixt and the firſt day of June next to come, in the year of God 1644. years.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing it is agreed and condeſcended unto, that the burthen be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to every mans eſtate, In that caſe it is declared, that when the whole valuations of the whole Kingdome ſhall be known in manner and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the rolls above ſpecified.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is appointed and ordained, that a ſurvey ſhall be made of the whole foreſaids Rols, and compared one with another, to the effect it may be ſeene and knowne, if any Shire or Shires have paid more out of the hundred marks (victuall and others commodities being turned into money) then other Shires have, and being ſo found, that ſome may be appointed before this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Convention diſſolve, or by the next Parliament, or by the Committees from either of them, to ſee what is the juſt proportion, which according to their foreſaids rents, would fall upon every Shire, that theſe who have payed more then their juſt proportion, may have repayment aff the Shires, who have paied leſſe, to be collected and inbrought by ſuch perſons as this preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, the Eſtates of Parliament, or Committees from either, ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the foreſaids whole ſums of money, as well to Burgh as Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, extends to a great ſumme of money, and will be a conſiderable burthen upon this Kingdom, and that the ſame is wholly paid out of the land rents, trade, burrow-lands, and other land rent, and yearly commoditie, without conſideration or laying any burthen upon money, upon bank, or anuall rent: Therefore it is ſtatute and ordained, Like as the ſaids Eſtates ſtatutes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains, that every debtour of money upon anuall rent, as well to Burgh as Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſhall have retention at the ſaid terme of Candlemas next, of ſix of each hundreth marks or pounds wherein he is lyable of annuall rent, to his Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors at the ſaid terme: Providing that the remanent of the ſaid annuall rent, out of the which the ſaid Debitour ſhal crave retention, ſhal be thankfully paid at the leaſt within three moneths after the ſaid terme of payment of the annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all rent, otherwiſe no retention to be allowed.</p>
            <p>And ſicklike it is hereby declared, that this preſent Act, nor no Clauſe therein, ſhall be any ground of ſuſpenſion to any Debtour for retention of the ſaid principall ſums addebted by him, and by-run annuall rents, but that every Creditour may ſute, crave, and charge for the ſame, after the day of payment thereof.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby declared, that if any perſon or perſons within or without Burgh, ſhall upon their Oath declare to their Magiſtrates within Burgh, and Commiſſioners of the Shires without Burgh, that they pay annual rent to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, dwelling without this Kingdome, of whom they cannot have retention foreſaid, in that caſe the ſaids Magiſtrates within Burgh, and Commiſſioners without Burgh, ſhall defaulk proportionally to the ſaids perſon or perſons, ſuch a part of their loane, as they ſhall finde agreeable to equity and reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152355:10"/>
            <p> And ſicklike, in reſpect that the foreſaids ſums of money ſo to be lent, are in hope of payment thereof from the Parliament of England:</p>
            <p>It is hereby declared, that the whole creditours within this Kingdome, as well to Burgh as Landward, who ſhall grant retention to their debtours, in manner foreſaid, ſhall have their proportionall repayment with the reſt of the Countrie, and that either from his debitours, if it pleaſe the creditour to truſt him therewith, or otherwiſe to take aſſignation from the debitour upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England, as a part of the ſame, due to the debitour for his relief.</p>
            <p>AND becauſe the enemies to Religion and Peace of this Kingdome, are daily making diviſions, and waiting all occaſions, whereby they may draw to factions, make inſurrections, and ſtir up others to the diſobedience of the laws, and common reſolution for the good of Religion, His Majeſties Honour and Safety, and the weale of this Kingdome:</p>
            <p>Therefore, and for the reaſons contained in the Act of the ſaids Eſtates, made anent the leavy of ſome Horſe and Foot, for preveening of any ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, diſtractions, inſurrections, factions, and diſobedience to the ſaids common reſolutions:</p>
            <p>The ſaids Eſtates have voluntarily granted, ſtatute and ordained, Like as they by thir preſents voluntarily grants, ſtatutes, and ordains, A taxt of 120000. l. Scots money, to be uplifted for the entertainment of the ſaids Men, Horſe and Foot to be levied, as ſaid is, in manner, and for the uſe contained in the ſaid Act. Which ſum of 120000. l. money foreſaid, ſhall be paid to the ſaid generall Collector, his Deputes and Officers, and others having power and warrand from him, at the ſaid terme of Candlemas next: <hi>viz.</hi> one ſixth part thereof, extending to the ſum of 20000. l. By the Burrowes of this Kingdom and the remanent thereof, extending to 100000 l. by the ſeverall Shires of this Kingdome, conform to a particular rool thereof, ſubſcribed by the ſaid Lord Chancellour in preſence of the Convention of Eſtates.</p>
            <p>For in bringing and ingathering whereof, the ſame maner of way ſhall be followed, and the ſame kinde of letters direct, the like diligence uſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, as for the foreſaids ſums of money hereby lent for the ſupply of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in Ireland, conform to the preceding tenour of this preſent Act.</p>
            <p>And it is ſtatute and ordained, that no ſuſpenſion ſhall be granted to any perſons whatſoever, without conſignation of the ſums charged for in the Clerk of the ſaid collection his hand, unleſſe the reaſons thereof can be inſtantly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified or made notour at the paſſing of the ſaid Bill, either <hi>in preſentia</hi> in the time of Seſſion, or by four or five of the Lords of Seſſion in time of vacance, To the which ſuſpenſions the ſaids Lords of Seſſion ſhall be onely Judges, in ſuch form and manner as they are, and have been in matters of Taxation.</p>
            <p>It is hereby ſtatute and ordained, that the generall Collector ſhall take ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and reſponſall caution from every Sub-collector to do his exact dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in every thing committed to his charge, as well in bringing in of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as in all other diligence, conforme to the bands to be made by them and their Cautioners thereanent.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe ſtatute and ordained, that the Collectors of every Pariſh ſhall either be a ſufficient and reſponſall man himſelfe, or otherwiſe ſhall give ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient caution for his intromiſſion and diligence, The which diligence to be done as well by the ſaids Sub-collectors, as by the ſaids Collectors of Pariſnes <hi>reffectivè,</hi> is hereby underſtood to be ail ordinary execution of horning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152355:11"/>in due time, and poynding, untill they be ſtopped by deforcement, are to be received for diligence alannerly.</p>
            <p>Likeas it is hereby ſtatute and ordained, that the ſaid Collector generall ſhall receive the ſaids diligence of regiſtrate hornings in due time, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of deforcement from the ſaids Sub-collectors and Collectors <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> providing the ſame be delivered to the ſaid Collectour generall, before the fifteenth day of March next to come, otherwayes no diligence to be received, but they to be liable for payment <hi>in ſolidum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is likewiſe ordained, that the Sub-collectors of every Parochine, ſhall not be obliged to cary the money received by them farther then their own Pariſh, and at fartheſt to the head Burgh of the Shire, and the Sub-collectour ſhall be obliged to receive the ſame, and make payment thereof to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Collectour, as is above ſpecified.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe who takes paines in the ſaid collection, as well the ſaid Sub-collectors, Collectors of Pariſhes, Clerks in the Shires, Clerk of the ſaid collection, and others to be imployed in the ſaid ſervice, will deſerve to have certain fees and allowance granted to them:</p>
            <p>It is therefore ſtatute and ordained, that ane roll be made thereof, either by the ſaids Eſtates, or by ſome to be appointed from them, which rolls being ſo made and ſet down, the ſame ſhall be regiſtred in the books of convention, and extracts given forth thereof, to the effect every man may know his own due</p>
            <p>It is hereby declared, that no exemption ſhall be granted to any perſon or perſons whatſoever, except onely the lands, rents, annuall rents, and others dueties mortified to Colledges, Schools, Hoſpitalls, and for upholding of Kirks and Bridges, and the Lord Chancellor, and fifeteen ordiner Lords of Seſſion allannerly.</p>
            <p>It is alwayes declared, that this preſent manned of ingathering of the ſaid loane and taxation ſhall no wayes prejudge any perſon whatſoever in ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding taxations, but that every mans right and claim, and all the prejudice that may ariſe anent the ſamine or manner thereof, whereby any man may inſtruct enorm leſion, and that he was unequally ſtented, is hereby ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially reſerved <hi>hinc inde.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Alex. Gibſone Cler. Regiſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at Edinburgh by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie, <hi>1647.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
